# Jonas Markussen

## R&D Software Engineer and PhD

#### SOFTWARE ENGINEERING EXPERIENCE

Software Architect Senior Software Engineer 2019 —

2018 — 2019

**Dolphin Interconnect Solutions** 

Contributed to the SmartIO framework for high-performance, distributed I/O and resource sharing, in PCIe shared-memory clusters. Gained experience with PCIe, non-transparent bridging, cluster interconnects, RDMA, distributed shared-memory architectures, NVMe, GPU programming, Nvidia GPUDirect, driver development and Linux kernel hacking.

- Contributed to the design, implementation and evaluation of SmartIO.
- Created a distributed device driver for simultaneous sharing of a non-SR-IOV NVMe among multiple hosts in a cluster.
- Implemented Linux KVM hypervisor support using VFIO mediated device drivers for assigning remote physical devices to VMs (pass-through).
- Developed a storage framework based on SmartIO and GPUDirect, providing zero-copy raw block access to NVMes from multiple GPUs in the cluster without involving CPU in the data path.
- Developed various DMA and RDMA cluster benchmarking tools.

## **Embedded & Systems Software Developer**

2014 — 2015

Bridgetech

Worked with online analysis of digital video over network. Got experience with video encoding, PIM-SM multicasting, MPEG streams, working with C++ in an embedded environment, and network traffic analysis.

- Contributed to an MPEG transport stream parser for the VB288 content extractor using libpcap for live capturing IPTV.
- Implemented a parser for MPEG-2 and MPEG-4/AVC video streams in order to extract and validate CEA608/708 closed captioning data and provide real-time event notifications.

#### **Software Development Engineer (Back-end)**

2013 - 2014

Fotoware

Worked mainly with FotoWeb, a web-based image and video archiving system with full-text metadata search and workflows based on metadata tags. Gained experience working with Apache2, MongoDB, web caches, designing REST services from the ground up, and creating HTTP endpoints with C++ (FastCGI) and Python (Flask).

- Implemented a hierarchical metadata taxonomy tree that supported CRUD operations and assignment to assets of tens of thousands of metadata tags within milliseconds.
- Created a configurable workflow engine allowing users to create custom pipelines and workloads for processing assets based on metadata tags.
- Made a background job scheduler with support for webhooks and asynchronous message-passing as well as bulk file operations.
- Implemented both back-end and front-end for exporting assets to an external CMS and an access management UI for these exports.

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- J. Markussen, L.B. Kristiansen, P. Halvorsen, H. Kielland-Gyrud, H.K. Stensland, C. Griwodz: SmartlO: Zero-overhead Device Sharing through PCIe Networking. ACM TOCS (2021). DOI: 10.1145/3462545
- J. Markussen, L.B. Kristiansen, R.J. Borgli, H.K. Stensland, F. Seifert, M. Riegler, C. Gri-wodz, P. Halvorsen: Flexible device compositions and dynamic resource sharing in PCle interconnected clusters using Device Lending. Cluster Computing (2020). DOI: 10.1007/s10586-019-02988-0
- J. Markussen, L.B. Kristiansen, H.K. Stensland, F. Seifert, C. Griwodz, P. Halvorsen: Flexible Device Sharing in PCle Clusters using Device Lending. ICPP Comp. (2018). DOI: 10.1145/3229710.3229759
- B.R. Opstad, J. Markussen, I. Ahmed, A. Petlund, C. Griwodz, P. Halvorsen: Latency and fairness trade-off for thin streams using Redundant Data Bundling in TCP. IEEE LCN (2015). DOI: 10.1109/LCN.2015.7366322

 +47 408 62 630 jonassm@ifi.uio.no jonasmarkussen enfiskutensykkel

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD, Informatics 2015 — University of Oslo & Simula Research Laboratory Doctorate degree in computer science.

MSc, Informatics 2010 — 2014 University of Oslo & Simula Research Laboratory Master's degree in computer science.

BSc, Informatics 2006 — 2010 University of Oslo Bachelor's degree in computer science.

#### OTHER JOB EXPERIENCE

Front-end Developer
Fotoware

Java Programmer
Redimi

Teaching Assistant
University of Oslo

2011 — 2013
2010 — 2011
2019 — 2011

### SKILLS

**System architecture** – Linux kernel hacking, device drivers, ATmega & STM32 microcontrollers, embedded, PCIe, KVM, virtual machines, memory and resource virtualization, memory architectures, non-transparent bridges, NVMe, GPUDirect, x86, ARM.

**Cluster computing & HPC** – distributed shared-memory applications, ultra low-latency networking, MPI, RDMA, interconnection networks, GPU programming (CUDA).

**IP networking** – routing protocols, transport protocols, TCP, multicasting, 802.11 WLAN family, MANETs, QoS, traffic engineering, libpcap, TCP congestion control, traffic analysis, AQMs.

**Web technologies** – HTTP, REST, Ajax, FastCGI, jQuery, SQL, HTML/CSS, MongoDB, Flask, Apache2, nginx, CDNs, web caching.

#### **PROJECTS**

**libnvm (formerly ssd-gpu-dma)** – A software library for developing user-space NVMe drivers and storage applications. Supports GPUDirect, enabling direct data transfer into GPU memory. https://github.com/enfiskutensykkel/ssd-gpu-dma

**analyseTCP** – Contributed to a TCP traffic analyser that looks at the per-byte latency from sent to received, useful for measuring the performance of time-dependent traffic.

https://github.com/enfiskutensykkel/analyseTCP